Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ס"ט, Samech Tes,
69, and we pick up four lines from the top, איתיבי אביי.
Aiteivi Abaye. We have just started בן סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer U'Moreh,
and we have positioned a debate because we had a teaching of
רב חסדא Rav Chisda that if a minor fathers a child, that
child cannot be a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh because it
says לאיש בן L'ish ben and a man has a son, not
a child has a son. And which the גמרא Gemara says obviously
means that he thinks that an underage child, somebody under the age
of 13, can father a child. And that was said to be
in conflict, or it's a debate between him and רבא Rava because
רבא Rava teaches based in the case of a גזל הגר, Gezel
HaGer, stealing from a גר ger and swearing falsely, and then the
גר ger dies, that you don't have to worry if the גר
ger has heirs if the גר ger was a minor because a
minor cannot father a child. So we have a debate between רבא
Rava and רב חסדא Rav Chisda whether a minor can father a
child. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Four
lines from the top, ס"ט עמוד א. Samech Tes amud aleph. איתיבי
אביי Aiteivi Abaye asked this. איש, Ish, it says איש, Ish, אין
לי אלא איש. Ein li ela ish. I only know that we're
talking about
a man. The context here is a case of a שפחה חרופה,
Shifcha Charufa, a slave woman who's sort of partly married to a
slave and a man sleeps with her and there's a special קרבן
korban for that case. So it says, and רש"י Rashi quotes פסוק,
pasuk, ואיש כי ישכב את אשה שכבת זרע, V'ish ki yishkav et
isha shichvat zera, and that literally, that's actually one of the places
where the תורה Torah explicitly describes it as שכבת זרע, shichvat zera,
you know, a sleeping of a seminal emission. And it's one of
the places where הלכה halacha actually requires that there be גמר ביאה,
gmar biah, not just העראה, ha'arah, where it be a full penetration.
Anyway, so אביי Abaye says איש, Ish, אין לי אלא איש. Ein
li ela ish. I only know that that case applies if it
is a man.
בן תשע שנים ויום אחד שראוי לביאה מנין? Ben tes shanim v'yom
echad she'rauy l'biah minayin? How do I know to even include a
case of somebody that is nine years old and one day which
as we know is defined as an act of intercourse? תלמוד לומר
ואיש. Talmud lomar v'ish. The extra ו. vav. אין לי אלא. Ein
li ela. So אמר ליה amlei יש לו ואינו מוליד. yesh lo
v'eino molid. So the point is that that is a פסוק pasuk
which says שכבת זרע shichvat zera and the requirement for שפחה חרופה
Shifcha Charufa is ראוי להוליד, rauy l'holid, excuse me, ראוי להזריע rauy
l'hazriya that you need גמר ביאה, gmar biah, you need a full
penetration because it is a context in which it's fit to be
to seminal emission to ejaculate. So the גמרא Gemara concedes that yes,
under 13 has seminal emission, but יש לו ואינו מוליד, yesh lo
v'eino molid, but it is not able to procreate. Okay, so there
is seminal emission but the semen is not potent yet, that is
the claim.
כצבועה שלא הביאה שליש, K'tzuva shelo hevi'a shlish, like grain that has
not yet become a third ripe. And in that case, you know,
there is grain there but it has not yet the ability, if
you were to plant the seed it would not bring about more
grain. Okay, so it's not yet fertile. דמי, Damye, it's
like that is what it can be compared to. דבי חזקיה תנא,
D'vei Chizkiya tanna, the house of Chizkiya taught, וכי יזיד איש, v'chi
yazid ish, if a man, you know, lies in wait, we just
had this in פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim, רעהו להרגו בערמה, are'ehu l'hargo
b'ormah, you know against his friend he willfully lies in wait against
his friend to kill him with deception, you know so then מעם
מזבחי תקחנו למות. me'im mizbechi tikachennu lamut. But we're making a דרש
drash on the word כי יזיד ki yazid and we'll see that
that's based like on the word ויזד יעקב נזיד, vayazed Yaakov nazid,
like cook. So let's take a look. וכי יזיד איש, V'chi yazid
ish, איש מזיד ומזריע, ish mezid u'mazria, a man, the semen sort
of inside of him, you know, ripens, cooks, and then he can
be fertile. ואין קטן מזיד ומזריע. V'ein katan mezid u'mazria. So it
has nothing to do with the פסוק pasuk which is talking about
somebody who kills במזיד, b'mezid, but from that word of כי יזיד
ki yazid we're learning out that only when you're a man can
you be fertile. אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי Amlei Rav Mordechai
l'Rav Ashi מאי משמע דהאי מזיד לישנא דבישולי הוא? mai mashma d'hai
mezid lishana d'bishulei hu? Where are you getting this דרשה drasha that
the word מזיד mezid is sense of, you know, cooking and ripening?
דכתיב ויזד יעקב נזיד. D'chtiv vayazed Yaakov nazid. Okay, so that is
consistent with the teaching of רבא Rava that only when somebody is
an adult, a man, only after the age of בר מצוה bar
mitzvah is his semen fertile. Of course, biologically it is not dependent
on that. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ותנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל V'tanna d'bei Rabbi Yishmael בן ולא אב. ben v'lo av.
So one minute, but we have a teaching of the house of
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says, you know,
that excludes the case of if the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer
U'Moreh himself has fathered a child. Okay, so until now we were
excluding the case of a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh who
had been fathered by a child. Here we are excluding the case
of when the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh himself has fathered
a child. Only if he is a son, not if he's already
a father. Okay, and so here again, even though now we know
that a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh is בר מצוה-ed, bar
mitzvah but still, is there enough time for him to father a
child if you say that his semen is only potent starting at
the age of בר מצוה? bar mitzvah? So let's... So let's take
a look.
בן ולא אב, Ben ve-lo av, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the
case? אילימא דעבר בתר דאייתי שתי שערות, Ileima de-avar battar de-aisi shte
searot, if the woman he
impregnated happened after he brought two pubic hair hairs,
so
meaning the conception happened once he was already an adult בר מצוה,
Bar Mitzvah, which is what we're claiming that it has to be
at that stage where the semen is potent. ואוליד מקמי דלהקיף זקן,
Ve-olid mikamei de-lahakif zakan, but now in order for him to be
a father, this woman has to give birth before his lower beard
fills out, okay? So מי קשות כולי האי? Mi kashos kulei hai?
But there's not enough time. The range of time, the amount of
time that a window that somebody could become a בן סורר ומורה
ben sorer u-moreh is very short. Why?
How do you know how long it's going to take for the
pubic hair to fill out? Well, דאמר רב כרוספדאי, De-amar Rav Kruspedai,
רב כרוספדאי Rav Kruspedai says, interesting, כרוספדאי Kruspedai is Aramaic for ציצית,
tzitzit, just a little interesting fun fact there, but doesn't רב כרוספדאי
Rav Kruspedai teach כל ימיו של בן סורר ומורה אינו אלא גמל
חדשים? Kol yamav she-ben sorer u-moreh eino ela gimmel chadashim? That a
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh from the time he's בר מצוה
Bar Mitzvah it's only three months. Now how that fits with our
משנה Mishnah that says when the pubic hair fills out, we'll worry
about in a minute. But for now, let's take the assumption that
that הלכה Halacha is true, that it can't be more than three
months. So if you say that when somebody is only able that
a man's semen, a boy's semen is only potent once he becomes
בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, there's no way we can exclude a בן
סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh who's a father, because he would have
had to father a child, he would have had to have intercourse
after he was בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, and then he would not
be able to be a father within the three month window. אלא
לאו, Ella lav, so the only case could be דעבר מקמי דלאייתי
שתי שערות ואוליד מקמי דלהקיף זקן. de-avar mikamei de-la-aisi shte searot ve-olid
mikamei de-la-akif zakan. Excuse me. So the only way that it could
be a case that he could be a father and possibly be
a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh is if he had intercourse
before he was בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah and then the woman gave
birth while he was still in the three month window. ושמע מינה
קטן מוליד, u-shema mina katan molid, and that shows that the semen
of a minor can be potent, that a minor can actually father
a child. So Gemara says לא, Lo, no, ועולם דעבר בתר דאייתי
שתי שערות. ve-olam de-avar battar de-aisi shte searot. The woman became pregnant
after he brought two hairs ואוליד בתר דאקף זקן, ve-olid battar de-akaf
zakan, and he gave birth after his pubic hair filled out and
after the three she gave birth, excuse me, and after the three
months. Okay, if that's so, then he already can't be a בן
סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh because it's more than three months. So
why do you need to exclude him from this דרשה drasha of
בן ולא אב? Ben ve-lo av? ודקשיא דרב כרוספדאי, Ve-di-kashya de-Rav Kruspedai,
you're bothered about רב כרוספדאי's Rav Kruspedai teaching that the whole window
is three
months. So or here anyway we're saying that the birth was after
anyway his pubic hair filled out. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki
asa Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came he explained
what this teaching was to exclude בן ולא אב. Ben ve-lo av.
אמרי במערבא, Amri be-ma'arava, what they say in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
is בן ולא הראוי לקרותו אב. ben ve-lo ha-ra'uy le-koryo av. We're
not saying that once he's a father he can't be a בן
סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, once he is a potential father he
can't be a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u-moreh. And that's actually
why רב כרוספדאי Rav Kruspedai says there's a three month window because
now we understand where that idea is coming from, because at what
stage would an adult boy be able to be called a father?
Well, 13 years and three months. Why? Because he could have intercourse
on the day of his בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, and assuming that
that is only when the semen becomes potent, and then it takes
three months for the woman to show that she's pregnant.
הלכתית, Halachically, there's a after three months the woman is seen to
be showing that she's pregnant, that has a lot of הלכה Halacha
implications that you can see it and it's visible at that time.
And at that stage, you say, oh, he's the father of that
baby that's going to be born. Okay, so that's where רב כרוספדאי
Rav Kruspedai gets his three months limit, that it's that so it's
not a problem at all. You're right, she will give birth after
the three month limit, but the exclusion is not that he's already
a father but that it limits the window until a time when
in theory he could be a father, because and that's three months
after his בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, theoretical called a father, not yet
actually be a father. Okay, and that's exactly the teaching of רב
כרוספדאי. Rav Kruspedai. גופא. Gufa. So very nice. So now we have
solved the problem and we have explained where רב כרוספדאי Rav Kruspedai
gets his teaching from, gets his הלכה Halacha from. Now let's go
back to that teaching. גופא. Gufa. אמר רב כרוספדאי אמר רב שבתי
כל ימיו של בן סורר ומורה אינו אלא גמל חדשים בלבד. Amar
Rav Kruspedai amar Rav Shabtai kol yamav she-ben sorer u-moreh eino ela
gimmel chadashim bilvad. Three months. And now we've explained why. והנן תנן,
Ve-hanan tenan, מלו גמל חדשים
מלו, malu gimmel chadashim malu, but our משנה Mishnah teaches only when
the beard fills out. So מר Mar says whichever one comes first.
גמל חדשים אף על גב דלא הקיף. Gimmel chadashim af al gav
de-lo hikif. So Gemara says, whichever,
I skipped a line. והנן תנן משיביא שתי שערות ועד
שיקיף זקן. Ve-hanan tenan mi-she-yavi shte searot ve-ad she-yakif zakan. הקיף זקן
Heikif zakan until the full beard fills out, so that's not three
months, that could be longer. So the גמרא Gemara says whichever one
comes first. הקיף זקן אף על גב דלא מלו, Heikif zakan af
al gav de-lo malu, if the beard fills out even if it's
not three months, מלו ג' חודשים דלא מלו ג' חודשים, malu gimmel
chodashim de-lo malu gimmel chodashim, excuse me, or מלו ג' חודשים אף
על גב דלא הקיף, malu gimmel chodashim af al gav de-lo heikif,
whichever one comes first, fine. And we now we know the reasons
why, why the filling out, he's no longer just at the cusp
of, he's not a בן ben that's just at the cusp of
being a man, he's a full man, and after three months he's
already ראוי לקרות אב. ra'uy likros av.
Okay. יתיב רב יעקב מן הפקוד קמיה דרבינא, Yasiv Rav Yaakov min
Ha-Pekod kamei de-Ravina, Rav Yaakov from Ha-Pekod was sitting in front of
רבינא, Ravina, ויתיב וקאמר משמיה דרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, ve-yasiv ve-ka'amar
mishmei de-Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua, שמע מינה מדרב קספאי, shema mina
mi-de-Rav Kuspai, we learn, can learn now from the teaching of רב
קספאי, Rav Kuspai, אמר רב שבתאי, amar Rav Shabtai, יולדת לשבעה אין
עוברה ניכר לשליש שמה, yoledet le-shiva ein ubar nikar le-shlish she-me-ha, from
this that, that a woman who,
so let's learn now from this statement that רב קספאי Rav Kuspai
says in the name of רב שבתאי Rav Shabtai that we said
earlier that it's only three months of the time of a בן
סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer U-Moreh, that from that we can infer that
כל יומת דבן סורר ומורה אינו אלא ג' חודשים בלבד. kol yomas
de-ben sorer u-moreh eino ela gimmel chodashim bilvad. I skipped a line.
שמע מינה מדרב קספאי, shema mina mi-de-Rav Kuspai, אמר רב שבתאי, amar
Rav Shabtai, יולדת לשבתא, yoledet le-shivta, לשבעה אין עוברה ניכר לשליש שמה,
le-shiva ein ubar nikar le-shlish she-me-ha, that if a woman were to
give birth in the seventh month or after seven months because the
גמרא Gemara understood that you know, a, that, that the גמרא Gemara
had a funny understanding that you could give birth like at the
end of nine months and at the end of seven months but
not like in your eighth month, that that actually the child would
not survive, but that's a whole different discussion. But that when a
woman does give birth in seven months that you would not say
that the fetus would be visible because you know, in a third
of that time. By a normal nine-month pregnancy we say the fetus
is visible in three months. So what would happen in the seventh
month pregnancy? Would the fetus be visible? Would everything be speeded up?
Would the fetus be visible in two and a third months or
would it only be visible in three months? So from the teaching
of רב קספאי Rav Kuspai in the name of רב שבתאי Rav
Shabtai you can, you can understand, you can figure out that even
in the case of a seven-month pregnancy the fetus is not visible
at a third of the time but only after three full months.
How do you figure that out? דאי סלקא דעתך עובר ניכר לשליש
שמה, de-isalka daitach ubar nikar le-shlish she-me-ha, because if in that case
the fetus would be visible after a third of the time, so
it would be parallel, you know, the same proportion of time as
a nine-month pregnancy, so למה לי ג', lama li gimmel, why would
the days of a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U-Moreh only be,
you know, why would they be limited to three months? בתרי ותילתא
סגי. betrei ve-tilsa sagi. His window should only be two and a
third. After two and a third months a בן סורר ומורה Ben
Sorer U-Moreh is ראוי לקרות אב. ra'uy likros av. Theoretically he could
be a father, he could have impregnated somebody the day he became
בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, and it could have been a case of
a seven-month pregnancy and it would have been visible in two and
a third months and that would be a time when it's already
fit to call him a father. So since we make the window
three months you see that no matter if the pregnancy is a
nine-month pregnancy or seven-month pregnancy the woman will only be, you know,
visible that she's pregnant will only be showing after three months. Okay,
that seems like a pretty good argument. אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back, לעולם אימא לך עובר ניכר לשליש שמה. lo'olam eima lach
ubar nikar le-shlish she-me-ha. I can tell you no, in the seven-month
pregnancy the fetus is visible in a third of the time in
two and a third months. וזי זיל בתר רובא, ve-zi zil basar
ruba, but why then did we say that the בן סורר ומורה
Ben Sorer U-Moreh is a three-month window and not a two and
a third months window? זיל בתר רובא, zil basar ruba, because you
go by the majority when you're trying to figure out when is
the time when it's fit to call him a father you say
in most circumstances he would not be able to be called a
father until, you know, until three months. So even though there's exceptions
to that rule you would define that period of ראוי לקרות, ra'uy
likros, excuse me, that of when he's still a בן ben and
not fit to be a father to extend for a full three
months. You go by the majority. So זיל בתר רובא. zil basar
ruba. אדרוה קמיה דרבינא, Adruh kamei de-Ravina, so they got, you know,
brought this answer back to
רבינא. Ravina. אמר ליה amar lei and he said to them ובדיני
נפשות אזלינן בתר רובא? u-be-dinei nefashos azinan basar ruba? I'm sorry, I
skipped a line again. זיל בתר רובא. zil basar ruba. אמרוה קמיה
דרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, amruha kamei de-Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua,
so they said this answer in front of רב הונא Rav Huna
the son of רב יהושע. Rav Yehoshua. אמר ליה amar lei and
he said back to them ובדיני נפשות מי אזלינן בתר רובא? u-be-dinei
nefashos mi azinan basar ruba? Why should you go by רוב? rov?
Right, we should, this is a case of a capital crime בן
סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U-Moreh and therefore we should try to limit
the ability to apply it. Life is at stake, it's a capital
crime and we should not go by majority and we should say
since it's possible to be a father to be called a father
at two and a third months, that should determine to make the
window even smaller. והתורה אמרה ve-ha-Torah amra and the Torah said ושפטו
העדה והצילו העדה, ve-shaftu ha-eida ve-hitzilu ha-eida,
that you have an obligation to try to save the person. Now
of course until now we've been dealing with that in the context
of the deliberations, but here it is sort of applying it even
in the context of the criteria to be found. finding somebody guilty.
And the שיעורים, shiurim, and of course we know that חז״ל Chazal
require witnesses and warning and the guy saying, I don't care. So
here it's saying we should not go even when we're deciding the
שיעור shiur of when is it fit to call him a father,
you know, when is he still able and you know when is
he still not fit, we should try to define that period of
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh as small as possible and not
go by רוב. rov. So את אמרת זיל בתר רובא? at amart
zil batar ruba? You're saying we should go by רוב? rov? אזלו
קמיה דרבינא, azlu kamey de-Ravina, so they went and they gave, you
know, they were sort of shuttling the back and forth
between Ravina and Rav Huna here. So they said back, said Ravina
here, Rav Huna says you shouldn't go by רוב, rov, you should
try, even you should go by the minority to try to shorten
the window. אמר ליה amar lei and Ravina said back, בדייני נפשות
לא אזלינן בתר רובא? bedayanei nefashot lo azlinan batar ruba? What? Do
you think we don't go by רוב rov by דיני נפשות, dinei
nefashot, by capital crimes? But we do! ותנן, v-tenan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, אחד אומר בשנים בחודש ואחד אומר בשלושה, echad omer
b-shnayim b-chodesh v-echad omer b-shlosha, עדותן קיימת. edutan kayemet.
If one person says that this guy killed somebody on the second
of the month, the other says it was on the third of
the month, you don't say that they're contradicting, you say that they're
actually testifying to the same thing. שזה יודע בעיבורו של חודש וזה
אינו יודע, shezeh yodeia b-iburo shel chodesh v-zeh eino yodeia,
because this one knows that it was a full month the month
before and the other one doesn't. So you know it's possible that
people are off by one day in terms of what day of
the month it is based on how long the month was before,
and you don't always know at the beginning of the month, you
know, maybe didn't get the news from בית דין. Beis Din. ואי
סלקא דעתך אם לא אמרינן זיל בתר רובא, v-i salka daitach im
lo amrinan zil batar ruba, if you were to say we never
go by majority in capital crimes because we're always looking for any
excuse to get the guy off, so נימא הני דווקא קמסהדי, neima
hanei davka k-mashadi, why don't we say that the witnesses are being
accurate, not that they're, one of them is off, ואכחושי הוא דקמכחשי
אהדדי, v-ach-chushi hu de-ka-machashi ahadadei,
they're contradicting one another. אלא לאו משום דאמרינן זיל בתר רובא ורובא
דאינשי עבדי דטעו בעיבורא דירחא, ela lav mishum de-amrinan zil batar ruba
v-ruba d-inshei avdi d-to-u b-ibura d-yarcha, it must be that no, even
by דיני נפשות dinei nefashot we go by majority and we say
that it's very likely, it's very common that people make a mistake
in terms of when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was, and therefore we
don't look at this as a contradiction. Okay, so, you know, now
this is a little bit different, I mean, I mean they're all
sort of the same, right? It's not like that we say if
there's the evidence, the preponderance of the evidence, the majority, it's 51
percent likely or even 70 percent likely he killed somebody, we're going
to kill him. Right? That's not what we're, you know, that we're
going to execute him. That's not what we're saying in זיל בתר
רובא. zil batar ruba. The זיל בתר רובא zil batar ruba here
is more sort of about like setting up the parameters, what to
define the period of time when he's not fit to be called
a father, go by the majority. What should be defined when you
say witnesses contradict one another? Only if, you know, they're clearly contradicting,
but if it's understandable that people make a mistake and otherwise everything
else they're saying is the same thing, then that doesn't define a
contradiction. Okay, so those types of things you can use the idea
of רוב. rov.
Okay. אמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah mi-Difti, אף אנן נמי
תנינא, af anan nami tanina, we also taught in the משנה, Mishnah,
בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד מתקדשת בביאה. bat shalosh shanim v-yom echad
mitkadeshet b-viah. So we've taught this earlier in the מסכת, masechet, it's
also משנה נדה. Mishnah Niddah. If a girl is three years old
and then she could be married off by her father through ביאה,
viah, meaning it's considered an act of intercourse and it works for
קידושין. kiddushin. ואם בא עליה יבם קנאה, v-im ba aleha yavam kna-ah,
and if the brother-in-law, you know, an act of יבום yibbum was
done where it's effected through an act of intercourse, then that is
effective once she's three years old and a day. וחייבין עליה משום
אשת איש, v-chayavin aleha mishum eshet ish, and if she was married
either through יבום yibbum or through ביאה viah or through any means
and then somebody had intercourse with her, he would be חייב chayav
for intercourse with a married woman and it would be an act
of intercourse and he'd be put to death. ומטמא את בועלה לטמא
משכב תחתון כעליון, u-metamei et bo-alah l-tamei mishkav tachton k-elyon, if she's
a נדה, niddah, then the one who has intercourse with a נדה
niddah is טמא, tamei, he becomes like her, an אב הטומאה, av
ha-tumah, not just like somebody who touched a נדה. niddah. And this
is defined as an act of intercourse and he becomes an אב
הטומאה, av ha-tumah, and even the things that he is sitting on,
the top thing and the bottom thing, and if he's sitting on
ten cushions, even the bottom one becomes טמא, tamei, it's like the
law of a משכב mishkav of a נדה niddah except it's one
degree removed, we won't go into that detail right now. ניסת לכהן
אוכלת בתרומה, niset l-kohen ochelet b-trumah, if she's married to a כהן,
kohen, she can eat תרומה trumah because, you know, for a woman
to eat תרומה trumah married to a כהן, kohen, at least rabbinically,
you require that it be חופה, chuppah, it be fit to have
ביאה, viah, and so since she's fit to have ביאה, viah, she
can eat from תרומה. trumah. בא עליה אחד מן הפסולים פסלה מן
הכהונה, ba aleha echad min ha-psulim pasla min ha-khunah,
if she has intercourse from somebody who is invalid for a כהן
kohen like a חלל chalal or a ממזר mamzer or whatever, then
that makes her invalid to marry a כהן. kohen. ואם בא עליה
אחד מכל העריות האמורות בתורה, v-im ba aleha echad mi-kol ha-arayot ha-amurot
ba-Torah, and if any one of the forbidden עריות arayot
has intercourse with her, מומתין עליה והיא פטורה, mumatin aleha v-hi pturah,
they would be put to death for cause of her because, you
know, it's intercourse again if it was a brother, a father, whatever,
not brother, that's not חייב מיתה chayav mitah whatever. Anyway, a father,
a case of a married, you know, she was a married woman,
etc., they would be put to death, she would be exempt obviously
that she's a minor. Okay, we've seen all of that before. Three
years and a day is considered an act of intercourse. How is
this relevant to us? So let's take a look here at the
top of ס"ט עמוד ב'. Sam-tet Amud-bet. ואמאי, Ve-amai, why is this
true? אימא Eima אילו נישאי illu nisei ודעתה דהכי לא קדיש. ve-da'ata
de-hachi lo kadish.
So why do we consider her to be a married woman and
when her father marries her off and the man who has intercourse
with her is חייב chayav because of אשת איש, eishes ish, because
of adultery, you know, if it turns out that she is an
אילונית aylonis which is somebody who is not only infertile but basically
has like male characteristics? We won't go into exactly what that is
right now, but under those circumstances we say that it was a
קידושי טעות. kiddushei taus. So it might turn out that the wedding
will be a קידושי טעות kiddushei taus and we're not concerned with
that. We say that that will be a rare exception and by
default we should assume that it is what it looks like, which
is that the קידושין kiddushin is good. And we're not going to
worry about some future thing which might make us revise our assumption
right now. ודעתה דהכי לא קדיש Ve-da'ata de-hachi lo kiddish and he
didn't marry if she were to turn out to be an אילונית.
aylonis. אלא לאו דאמרינן זיל בתר רובא. Ella lav damrinan zil basar
ruba. You see that even by דיני נפשות dinei nefashos we go
by רוב. rov. Again, רוב rov that let us assume the basic
parameters are as we see them and we don't have to worry
about some of those other possibilities. ורוב נשים לאו אילונית נינהו Ve-rov
nashim lav aylonis ninhu and most of them are not an אילונית.
aylonis. So that seems to be another good proof to that. So
גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, מאי חייב עליה דקתני קרבן. mai chayav
aleha de-katani korban. No, no, no. When it says you're חייב chayav
it doesn't mean that we would execute somebody, it means they bring
a קרבן korban if it was שוגג. shogeg. So גמרא Gemara says
you can't say that. והא מוסן על ידה קתני. Ve-ha musan al
yadah katani. It says that they are executed for her so we're
talking about actually דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. בבא על אביה. Be-ba al
aviha. No,
we're not talking about a case of קידושין, kiddushin, maybe we would
say she might not be מקדשת mekudeshes because it'll turn out to
be קידושי טעות. kiddushei taus. We're talking about a case that her
father had intercourse with her and it's a case of one of
an עריות arayos of, you know, incest. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, והא אם בא על אחת מכל העריות קתני. ve-ha im ba
al achas mi-kol ha-arayos katani. מכל העריות קתני. Mi-kol ha-arayos katani. It
says if any one of the עריות, arayos, actually they could have
also referred to earlier in the משנה mishna where it says אשת
איש. eishes ish. Anyway, so clearly we're including a case of marriage
and you see we're not worried that she might turn out to
be an אילונית. aylonis. Okay, so this is interesting because we're saying
we do go by דיני נפשות dinei nefashos after רוב, rov, but
you might remember there's סוגיא sugyas in בבא קמא Bava Kama whatever
that we don't even go by דיני ממונות dinei mamanos after רוב.
rov. So how could you not go by דיני ממונות dinei mamanos
after רוב rov but you could go by דיני נפשות? dinei nefashos?
Right? Obviously you should protect life more than you protect money. But
part of the answer is that this is where we're just setting
basic parameters. You know, it's not considered a הכחשה hakchasha if people
normally make a mistake. It's so when we want to define what
is the period you're fit to be called a son and not
fit to be called a father, we'll define it by the majority.
Somebody had a קידושין, kiddushin, we're going to go by that definition
right now and not worry that of a small chance that something
in the future might cause us to reassess. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ella, but the גמרא Gemara has
this still a way to get out of this. הכא במאי עסקינן
דקיבליה ליה. Hecha be-mai askinan de-kibblei lei. No, maybe we're talking about
that he explicitly said I'm marrying you even if you turn out
to be an אילונית. aylonis. So you can't prove from this that
we go by רוב. rov. It might be a case where he
explicitly said I'm willing to accept it even if it turns out
to be otherwise.
Okay. תנא רבנן, Tanan rabanan, our
rabbis taught. המסוללת בבנה קטן, Ha-mesuleles be-vinah katan, if a woman is
המסוללת, mesuleles, you know, that's a phrase that's could be used, you
know, in a very, רש"י Rashi says לשון פריצות, lashon pritzus, specifically
like engaging in sexual behavior. It could just mean sort of, you
know, very close intimate physical contacts. Maybe it doesn't mean that it
was intentionally sexual. But one way or the other, a woman is
being like naked together with her minor son. והערה בה Ve-herah bah
and he went ahead and he penetrated her. הערה Ha-arah is just
barely penetrated, just inserting of the tip of the penis. בית שמאי
אומרים פסלה מן הכהונה. Beis Shammai omrin paslah min ha-kehunah. She's now
is invalid to marry a כהן, kohen, right, even if she was
a case where whatever her husband were to die and she would
be an אלמנה almanah or maybe she's not even married now. Anyway
she now has had intercourse with her son and that makes her
that invalidates her for a כהן. kohen. בית הלל מכשירין Beis Hillel
machshirin and בית
הלל Beis Hillel says no, she's still כשר. kosher. Why could that
be? I mean she actually did have intercourse and you know and
with somebody who is a what do you call it which is,
you know, would invalidate her. Ah, but the question is how old
is the son? By we've been saying that, you know, it's only
considered an act of intercourse with the boy once he's nine years
old. So now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to try to explain what
their debate is. אמר רבי חייא בריה דרבה בר נחמני אמר רב
חסדא ואמרי לה אמר רב חסדא אמר זעירי. Amar Rebbe Chiya brei
de-Ravba bar Nachmani Amar Rav Chisda va-amrei lah Amar Rav Chisda Amar
Ze'iri. הכל מודים בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד. Ha-kol modim be-ven tish'a
shanim ve-yom echad.
So these various אמוראים amoraim say everybody would agree that once the
son was nine years old and one day שביאתו ביאה she-bi'aso bi'ah
that that's an act of intercourse and, you know, and whether it
was intentional or non-intentional she she's now invalid to a כהן. kohen.
פחות מבן שמונה שאין ביאתו ביאה Pachus mi-ben shemoneh she-ein bi'aso bi'ah
and everybody also agrees that under eight years old it's not an
act of intercourse. לא נחלקו אלא בבן שמונה, Lo nechelku ella be-ven
shemoneh, the debate is eight years old and a day until nine.
Nine years old and one day, שביאתו ביאה, shebiuso biah, that that's
an act of intercourse and whether it was intentional or non-intentional, she's
now invalid to a כהן. Kohen. פחות מבן שמונה, pachus miben shemonah,
שאין ביאתו ביאה, she-ein biuso biah, and everybody also agrees that under
eight years old, it's not an act of intercourse. לא נחלקו אלא
בבן שמונה, lo nechleku ela beven shemonah, the debate is eight years
old and a day until nine years old and a day. Okay,
בית שמאי סברי Beis Shammai savri גמינן מדורות הראשונים, geminan midoros harishonim,
ובית הלל סברי uVeis Hillel savri לא גמינן מדורות הראשונים. lo geminan
midoros harishonim. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says we learn from earlier generations.
The גמרא Gemara is going to show how we can infer from
certain פסוקים psukim that even an eight year old child in the
past
could actually, this is going to get back to the issue of
father children, but we're going to see even an eight year old
child could father children so therefore it would be considered an act
of intercourse certainly.
And בית שמאי Beis Shammai says we learn from that example and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says we don't learn from that example right
now, we go by our מציאות metzius right now, whatever was in
the past was in the past. In the biblical times they lived
hundreds of years also, so that's not going to define for us,
for us it's going to be nine years and a day. But
as we said, it will be interesting because the גמרא Gemara will
at least say that certainly at least in the past, not only
eight years and a day was an act of intercourse, but actually
could father a child. Okay, it's actually a little bit strange that
this seems to be that the גמרא Gemara is framing the debate
about eight years and a day to nine years, because then why
is it given specifically in this context of a mother who's being
intimate with her son? Why didn't it just talk about the regular
debate of when is the act of sex of an underage boy
considered an act of sex? But that's the way the גמרא Gemara
is choosing to frame the debate. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, ודורות ראשונים מנלן דאולוד, vedoros rishonim minalan de'olid, where
do you know that the earlier generations gave birth at eight years
old? אילימא מדכתיב הלא זאת בת שבע בת אליעם אשת אוריה החתי,
eileima midichsiv halo zos Bas Sheva bas Eliam eshes Uriah haChiti,
so here בת שבע Bas Sheva is the daughter of אליעם, Eliam,
the wife of אוריה החתי, Uriah haChiti, וכתיב אליעם
בן אחיתופל הגילוני, uchisiv Eliam ben Achitofel haGiloni, so אליעם Eliam was
the son of אחיתופל, Achitofel, so בת שבע Bas Sheva is the
granddaughter of אחיתופל. Achitofel. וכתיב וישלח ביד נתן הנביא ויקרא שמו ידידיה
בעבור
ה'
אהבו, uchisiv vayishlach beyad Nasan haNavi vayikra shemo Yedidiah ba'avur Hashem ahevo,
okay and this is talking about the birth of שלמה Shlomo who
was called ידידיה Yedidiah because God, ידיד ה', Yedid Hashem, God loved
him, that was born to בת שבע. Bas Sheva. וכתיב ויהי לשנתים
ימים ויהיו גוזזים לאבשלום. uchisiv vayehi lishnosayim yamim vayihyu gozzim leAvshalom.
So now we're going to see, we're going to sort of try
to explain we'll be stringing פסוקים psukim together to show that שלמה
Shlomo who was born to בת שבע Bas Sheva who we see
was the granddaughter of what's his name, of אחיתופל. Achitofel. So we're
going to see that שלמה Shlomo was seven years old when אחיתופל
Achitofel died and we'll see the age of אחיתופל Achitofel and that'll
sort of lead us back to figuring out when אחיתופל Achitofel had
children. So just sort of hold on and follow me here. Okay,
so וכתיב ויהי לשנתים ימים, uchisiv vayehi lishnosayim yamim,
so two years after שלמה Shlomo was born, ויהיו גוזזים לאבשלום vayihyu
gozzim leAvshalom and they were shearing the sheep for אבשלום. Avshalom. וכתיב
אבשלום ברח וילך גשור ויהי שם שלש שנים uchisiv Avshalom barach vayelech
Geshur vayehi sham shalosh shanim and then אבשלום Avshalom ran away, whatever
the whole thing was with fighting for the throne, anyway three years,
so now שלמה Shlomo was five years old in this as we're
stringing together the years mentioned in the various narratives. וכתיב וישב אבשלום
בירושלים שנתים ימים ופני המלך לא ראה uchisiv vayeshev Avshalom b'Yerushalayim shnatayim
yamim ufnei hamelech lo ra'ah and then he came back and he
was brought back and he didn't
see his father King David for two years. So now anyway שלמה
Shlomo was seven years old. וכתיב ויהי מקץ ארבעים שנה uchisiv vayehi
mikeitz arbaim shanah and it was after forty years, okay that's for
the forty years from the time they asked for a king, not
forty years from our chronology, so bracket the forty years. ויאמר אבשלום
אל המלך אלכה נא ואשלם את נדרי אשר נדרתי לה' בחברון. vayomer
Avshalom el hamelech elcha na va'ashalem es nidri asher nadarti l'Hashem b'Hevron.
וכתיב ואחיתופל ראה כי לא נעשתה עצתו. uchisiv v'Achitofel ra'ah ki lo
ne'esah atzaso.
So anyway here it was that after the seven years and אבשלום
Avshalom was back to ירושלים Yerushalayim and now אחיתופל Achitofel saw that
his whole plan was not done. I don't want to get into
all the whole narrative here the תנ"ך. Tanach. ויחבש את החמור ויקם
וילך אל ביתו vayachavosh es hachamor vayakam vayelech el beiso
he saddled up his donkey, he went to his house. ואל עירו
ויצו אל ביתו v'el iro vayitzav el beiso and he gave his
final orders. ויחנק vayichanek and he strangled himself. Okay so the key
is שלמה Shlomo was seven years old when אחיתופל Achitofel died, committed
suicide. וכתיב uchisiv now how old was אחיתופל? Achitofel? אנשי דמים ומרמה
לא יחצו ימיהם, anshei damim umirmah lo yechetzu yemeihem, men of blood
and deceit they won't live half their days. ותניא כל שנותיו של
דואג אינן אלא שלשים וארבע vesanya kol shnosav shel Doeg einan ela
shloshim v'arba so for a person ימי שנותינו בהם שבעים שנה yemei
shnosinu bahem shivim shanah if seventy years was considered the norm so
they don't get the half they don't get to thirty five, so
we have a tradition that דואג Doeg who also man of deceit
and blood lived only to thirty four years old. ושל אחיתופל אינן
אלא שלשים ושלש v'shel Achitofel einan ela shloshim v'shalosh and אחיתופל Achitofel
was thirty three. So that's the key, אחיתופל Achitofel died at the
age of thirty three when שלמה Shlomo was seven years old. So
כמה הוי להו תלתין ותלת kamah havay lehu talsin v'salas he was
thirty three. דל שבע דהוי שלמה, dal sheva d'havay Shlomo, שלמה Shlomo
was seven years old when that happened, so now subtract seven, so
we're twenty six. אחיתופל Achitofel was twenty six when his granddaughter בת
שבע Bas Sheva gave birth to שלמה. Shlomo. Okay, דל תרתי שני
לתלתי
עיבורי dal sarti shani letalsi iburei and for the pregnancies there has
to be
if אחיתופל Achitofel gave birth to אליעם Eliam and אליעם Eliam gave
birth to... first בת שבע *Batsheva* or birthed, and בת שבע *Batsheva*
gave birth to שלמה *Shlomo*, so that's three births that happened there,
and that's three per, so that's three nine month periods, that's more
or less two years. So subtract two years for the three pregnancies,
אשתכח *Ishtakach* so now we're down to 24. אשתכח דכל חד וחד
בתמני אוליד *Ishtakach d'chol chad v'chad b'tamni olid*, each generation gave birth
at eight. Okay, אחיתופל *Achitophel* at eight years old impregnated a woman
when he was nine roughly she gave birth to אליעם *Eliam* his
son, אליעם *Eliam* when he was eight and אחיתופל *Achitophel* was 17
impregnated a woman when now אחיתופל *Achitophel* is 18 his son was
born, בת שבע *Batsheva* was born. Then eight then בת שבע *Batsheva*
was eight so then according to this בת שבע *Batsheva* was eight
when דוד *David*
saw whatever and then got pregnant and gave birth and then got
pregnant for a year and gave birth when she was nine and
אחיתופל *Achitophel* was 26. And then that means that he was 33
when he committed suicide. Okay, so each generation there either sired a
child or gave birth to a child at eight months. All right,
where were we? לתלתא עיבורי אשתכח דכל חד וחד בתמני אוליד *Litlasa
iburei ishtakach d'chol chad v'chad b'tamni olid*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
מימאי *Mimay*, how do you know that? דילמא תרווייהו בתשע אוליד *Dilma
tarvaihu b'taysha olid*, maybe the two men in that chain gave birth
at sired at nine years old because our focus is on the
men. ובת שבע אוליד בשיש *U'Batsheva olid b'shish* and בת שבע *Batsheva*
gave birth at six years, right, so maybe men it took them
till nine years but בת שבע *Batsheva* was even younger and then
when you add them up you still get to your 24. משום
דאיתתא בריא *Mishum d'itata barya* because a woman is more strong than
men. תדע דההוא ולד מעיקרא *Teda d'hahu vlad meikara* because בת שבע
*Batsheva* anyway there was a child that died before שלמה *Shlomo*. So
it's not going to work anyway it's going to get even younger
than eight. So you're going to have to say that בת שבע
*Batsheva* was very young and then you could say that the two
men in this equation were both nine years old.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* now tries to learn it out from
another passage in the תנ"ך *Tanach*. So אלא מהכא Mehacha, *Ela mehacha*,
let's learn it out from here. אלה תולדות תרח תרח הוליד את
אברם את נחור ואת הרן Haran *Eileh toldos Terach Terach holid es
Avram es Nachor v'es Haran*. All right, so we all know that.
ואברם גדול מנחור שנה ונחור גדול מהרן שנה *V'Avram gadol mi'Nachor shana
v'Nachor gadol me'Haran shana* so we're going to assume that these are
being listed in age order so אברם *Avram* was and somehow we're
assuming that they're only one year apart or maybe that's the minimum
assumption. Okay, so הרן Haran *Haran* is two years younger than אברם
*Avram*. ונמצא אברם גדול שתי שנים מהרן *V'nimtza אברם Avram gadol shtei
shanim me'Haran*, so he's two years older than הרן Haran *Haran*. וכתיב
U'chtiv, ויקח אברם ונחור להם נשים *U'ksiv vayikach Avram v'Nachor lahem nashim*
and they took wives, ושם אשת אברם שרי ושם אשת נחור מלכה
בת הרן Haran. אבי מלכה ואבי יסכה Yiscah *v'shem eshes Avram Sarai
v'shem eshes Nachor Milkah bas Haran avi Milkah v'avi Yiskah*. So the
end of that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is that we know that יסכה
*Yiskah* was a daughter of הרן Haran, *Haran*, אברם *Avram*'s brother. ואמר
רבי יצחק יסכה זו שרה Sarah. *V'amar Rabi Yitzchak Yiskah zu Sarah*
and יסכה *Yiskah* is associated with שרה Sarah, *Sarah*, I mean also
why else is the תורה Torah *Torah* telling us its name so
you can understand why חז"ל *Chazal* want to identify that with her
with שרה *Sarah*. ולמה נקרא שמה יסכה שסוכה ברוח הקודש *V'lama nikra
shema Yiskah she'socha b'Ruach HaKodesh* that she could see with the רוח
הקודש *Ruach HaKodesh*, okay. So now we have אברם *Avram* is married
to הרן Haran *Haran*'s daughter, שרה *Sarah* is הרן Haran *Haran*'s daughter.
והיינו דכתיב כל אשר תאמר אליך שרה שמע בקולה *V'hainu d'chsiv kol
asher tomar eilecha Sarah shema b'kola* and that's why you have to
listen to שרה *Sarah* because she was she had נבואה *nevuah* she
had רוח הקודש *Ruach HaKodesh* even greater than אברם *Avram* according to
that. Okay, דבר אחר יסכה שהכל סוכין ביופיה *Davar acher Yiskah shehakol
sochin b'yofya* or יסכה *Yiskah* to mean to look but not that
she looks with רוח הקודש *Ruach HaKodesh* but everybody looks at her
beauty. Okay, fine. So שרה *Sarah* is יסכה *Yiskah*, שרה *Sarah* is
the daughter of הרן Haran *Haran*, אברם *Avram*'s younger brother by two
years. ויפול אברהם Avraham על פניו ויצחק ויאמר בלבו הלבן מאה שנה
יולד ואם שרה בת תשעים שנה תלד *Vayipol Avraham al panav vayitzchak
vayomar b'libo haleven me'ah shana yivaled v'im Sarah bas tishim shana seiled*.
So אברהם Avraham *Avraham* was 100 and שרה *Sarah* was 90. כמה
קשיש אברהם Avraham משרה עשר שנים *Kama kashish Avraham mi'Sarah eser shanim*,
so he's 10 years older than שרה *Sarah*. וקשיש מאבוה תרתי שני
*V'kashish me'avuha tarti shnei* and he is two years older than שרה
*Sarah*'s father, right, he's the oldest son, he's two years older than
הרן *Haran* and he's 10 years older than שרה *Sarah*. Okay, אשתכח
דאולידה הרן לשרה בתמני אולידה *ishtakach d'olidah Haran l'Sarah b'tamni olidah*, so
if that's true when הרן *Haran* sired שרה *Sarah*, הרן *Haran* had
to be eight years old because why? Because
he
was eight years old and אברהם Avraham *Avraham* at that age would
have been 10 and שרה *Sarah* would be born, so there you
have אברהם Avraham *Avraham* 10 years older than שרה *Sarah*. Actually it's
a little bit of a problem because it means he got his
wife pregnant at seven but okay maybe we're being a little like
nine months we're not being exact. Anyway, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: מימאי *Mimay*. So how do you know that's how the
math works? דלמא אברהם Avraham. זוטא דאחוה הוה. Maybe הרן was the
older brother and אברהם was the younger brother and we don't know
how many years older הרן was so you can't learn out anything
from how old הרן was when he gave birth to when he
sired שרה. ודרך חכמתם קחשיב להו, V'derech chachmatam k'chashiv lehu,
and the תורה is enumerating them, אברהם is listed first not because
he's the oldest, but because he's the wisest or the most important.
ותידע דקחשיב להו כדרך חכמתם דכתיב V'teda d'kachashiv lehu k'derech chachmatam d'chtiv
and we know sometimes the פסוקים Psukim list children not in order
of their age but in order of their wisdom or in order
of their stature as it says, ויהי נח בן חמש מאות שנה
ויולד נח את שם את חם ואת יפת, Vayehi Noach ben chamesh
me'ot shana vayoled Noach et Shem et Cham v'et Yephet, שם קדים
לחם שנה וחם קדים ליפת שנה. Shem qadim l'Cham shana v'Cham qadim
l'Yephet shana. So if we're going to assume age order, שם Shem
is one year older and we're somehow going to assume sequential like
we did before, שם Shem is one year older than חם, Cham,
חם Cham one year older than יפת. Yephet. נמצא שם גדול מיפת
שתי שנים. Nimtza Shem gadol mi-Yephet shtei shanim.
Just like we said by אברהם and הרן. וכתיב נח בן שש
מאות שנה והמבול היה מים על הארץ. U'chtiv Noach ben shesh me'ot
shana v'hamabul haya mayim al ha'aretz. Alright, נח Noach was 600.
וכתיב, U'chtiv, and we know נח Noach gave birth when he was
500 years to שם Shem and then חם Cham and then יפת.
Yephet. וכתיב אלה תולדות שם שם בן מאת שנה ויולד את ארפכשד
שנתים אחר
המבול. U'chtiv eileh toldot Shem Shem ben me'at shana vayoled et Arpachshad
shnatayim achar hamabul. שם Shem was 100 years and he gave birth
to ארפכשד Arpachshad two years after the מבול, Mabul, so it sounds
like he was 98 at the time of the מבול, Mabul, but
according to the פסוקים, Psukim, if he gave birth two years after
and then he was 100, but if we assume that נח Noach
gave birth to them in order, שם Shem was born when נח
Noach was 500 then שם Shem and נח Noach was when נח
Noach is 500 and the מבול Mabul was when נח Noach was
600, then שם Shem should have been 100 years old. במאה ותרתין
שנין הוי. B'me'ah v'tartein shanin hava.
What do you mean he was 100 years old? I mean 100
years old when the מבול Mabul was over and 102 two years
after the מבול. Mabul. במאה ותרתין שנין הוי. B'me'ah v'tartein shanin hava.
אלא דרך חכמתם קחשיב להו, Ela derech chachmatam k'chashiv lehu,
so when it says שם חם ויפת, Shem Cham v'Yephet, it's not
listing them in the order of their birth order but in the
order of their stature. הכא נמי דרך חכמתם קחשיב להו, Hacha nami
derech chachmatam k'chashiv lehu, here too by אברהם and הרן, so you
cannot have it that even if יסכה is שרה, you cannot say
that אברהם was older and that הרן had to have her when
he was born when הרן her father was eight years old. That
you cannot prove because הרן might have been older than אברהם. אמר
רב כהנא אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד, Amar Rav Kahana amritah l'shma'ta
k'mei d'Rav Zvid, so we haven't really proven that
דורות ראשונים dorot rishonim sired at eight years old. אמר רב כהנא
אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד מנהרדעא אמר לי אתון מהכא מתניתון ואנן
מהכא מתנינן לה. Amar Rav Kahana amritah l'shma'ta k'mei d'Rav Zvid mi-Nahardea
amar li atun mehacha masnitun v'anan mehacha masninan lah.
You try to prove it from those פסוקים Psukim and
here's where we bring it from. ולשם יולד גם הוא אבי כל
בני עבר אחי יפת הגדול. U'l'Shem yulad gam hu avi kol b'nei
Ever achi Yephet hagadol. שם Shem was born to him, the father
of all those from the other side of the river, עבר, Ever,
or the brother of יפת הגדול. Yephet hagadol.
So יפת הגדול שבאחיו הוי. Yephet hagadol she'b'achiv hava. And so now
אחי יפת הגדול achi Yephet hagadol it sounds like, maybe הגדול hagadol
could refer to שם, Shem, but the simple sense is יפת Yephet
the older one. So he says, so look from over there, excuse
me, we don't see here the eight years old. From over there
is where we see also that שם חם ויפת Shem Cham v'Yephet
are not listed in order because the later פסוק pasuk says יפת
הגדול. Yephet hagadol. Okay, so we cannot prove that this idea based
on the name that they're listed that that's the birth order, so
we still don't know that they gave birth at eight years old.
אלא מנלן? Ela minlan?
So where do you know it? מהכא, from here. ובצלאל בן אורי
בן חור למטה יהודה. U'Betzalel ben Uri ben Chur l'mateh Yehuda. So
בצלאל Betzalel was the son of אורי Uri the son of חור.
Chur. וכתיב ותמת עזובה, U'chtiv vatamot Azuvah, so עזובה Azuvah died. ויקח
לו כלב את אפרת ותלד לו את חור. Vayikach lo Kalev et
Ephrat vateled lo et Chur.
So חור Chur now we are going to find out is the
son of כלב. Kalev. בצלאל Betzalel was בן אורי בן חור, ben
Uri ben Chur, and חור Chur was the son of כלב. Kalev.
וכי עבד בצלאל משכן בר כמה הוי בר תליסר. V'ki avad Betzalel
mishkan bar kama hava bar tlissar.
Now when בצלאל Betzalel made the משכן, Mishkan, he had to be
at least 13. דכתיב איש איש ממלאכתו אשר המה עושים, D'chtiv ish
ish mimlachto asher heimah osim, each man. ותניא שנה ראשונה עשה משה
משכן שניה הקימו משכן ושלח
מרגלים. V'tanya shana rishona asah Moshe Mishkan shnia heqimo Mishkan v'shalach meraglim.
First year he made the משכן, Mishkan, second year they sent the
מרגלים. Meraglim. וכתיב,
so בצלאל Betzalel will be minimum 14 years old when the מרגלים
Meraglim were sent. וכתיב בן ארבעים שנה אנכי בשלח
משה עבד ה'. U'chtiv ben arba'im shana anochi b'shloach Moshe eved Hashem.
And the פסוק also says that כלב Kalev says I was 40
years when he was sent as the מרגל. Meragel. ועתה הנה אנכי
היום בן חמש ושמונים שנה. V'ata hinei anochi hayom ben chamesh u'shmonim
shana.
That's not relevant for us. כמה הוי להו ארבעין. Kama hava lehu
arba'in. So he was 40 years when he was sent as the
מרגל. Meragel. דל ארבעסר דהוי בצלאל, Dal arbassar d'hava Betzalel,
minus 14 that was בצלאל, Betzalel, בצלאל Betzalel was born 14 years
before. So 14 years earlier when כלב Kalev was 26, בצלאל Betzalel
was born. פשו לה עשרין ושית. Pashu lah esrin v'shit. דל תרתי
שני דתלתא עיבורי. Dal tartei shnei d'tlata iburei. Now we're going to
have to go from כלב Kalev would have to have חור, Chur,
חור Chur would have to have... אורי *Uri*, אורי *Uri* would have
to have בצלאל *Bezalel*. That's three births, so three births, nine months
per birth, that's minus two years like we did before. So where
are we? Hold on. דעל ביעתא דהוי בצלאל *D'al beita d'havi Bezalel*,
פשו ליה עשרין ושית *Pashu lei esrim v'shesh*, דל תרתי שני דתלתא
עיבורי *Dal tartei shinei d'tlata iburei*. So subtract two years for the
three pregnancies. אישתכח דכל חד וחד בתמני אוליד *Ishtakach dechol chad v'chad
batmanei aulid*. So each one gave birth at eight years old, right?
Because then you have בצלאל *Bezalel* to אורי *Uri*, אורי *Uri* to
חור *Chur*, excuse me, כלב *Kalev* to חור *Chur*, חור *Chur* to
אורי *Uri*, אורי *Uri* to בצלאל *Bezalel*. And all of that has
to be done in twenty-four years, so each one was eight years
old. That is the debate of בית הלל *Beit Hillel*, בית שמאי
*Beit Shammai*, do we learn from דורות הראשונים *Doros harishonim* or not?
Okay. Back to the משנה *Mishna*. בן ולא בת *Ben v'lo bat*.
So בן סורר ומורה *Ben Sorer u'Moreh* could only be a boy,
not a daughter, not a girl. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in the
ברייתא *Baraita*, אמר רבי שמעון *Amar Rabbi Shimon* בדין הוא שתהא בת
ראויה להיות כבן סורר ומורה *Badin hu she'tehei bat reuyah lihyot ke'ben
sorer u'moreh*. Logically, a daughter should be able to also be a
בן סורר ומורה *Ben Sorer u'Moreh*, שכל מצוין אצלה בעבירה *She'kol metzuyin
etzla ba'aveirah*. Because if the concern of a בן סורר ומורה *Ben
Sorer u'Moreh* is that, you know, if he's going on this wrong
path, he's going to lead a life of sin, so you know,
if a woman goes on the wrong path, she could turn to
prostitution. So that's a real concern. Now, of course that's not the
exact same as the concern of a בן סורר ומורה *Ben Sorer
u'Moreh* will go and actually be a bandit and kill people. But
anyway, אלא גזירת הכתוב הוא *Ela gezerat hakatuv hu* בן ולא בת
*Ben v'lo bat*. Even if there is more reason, it's the פסוק
*Pasuk* is clear,
only a son, not a daughter. Okay, we will end here.